April 2023 Protests; Collection ua600.007
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
April 2023 Protests Collection
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
State University of New York at Albany, Department of Women's, Gender and Sexuality Studies.
ua600.007
2.22 GB
This collection contains the materials related to the oral history accounts of two political protests that occured in the Spring 2023 semester at UAlbany. These accounts were gathered via interview by members of Dr. Rajani Bhatia's Women's, Gender and Sexuality Studies Research Seminar class.
Biographical / Historical
On April 4, 2023, the Turning Point USA's (TPUSA) chapter at the University at Albany (UAlbany) held a "Free Speech" event with guest speaker Ian Haworth. This event was protested by various members of the UAlbany community alleging that the event created an unwelcome space for the LBTQA+ community on campus. The protest included members of the UAlbany Chapter of Young Democratic Socialists of America (YDSA) which is affiliated with the Democratic Socialists of America.
The "Free Speech" Event hosted about fifteen participating students while over one hundred students attended in protest. The University Police Department eventually moved the event from the transfer lounge, when the protesters prevented the event from proceeding, to the third floor where there was more controlled access. Two student protesters were arrested for their participation, one for disorderly conduct and the other for second degree governmental obstruction. The protest began to disperse after three hours.
On April 14, 2023, the Created Equal and New York State Right to Life groups gathered on the UAlbany campus for a Pro-Life event. The event included a television display of abortion-related imagery and group members approaching passerby students with pamphlets and questions. The event began at 9 AM and by 1 PM, one hundred students had gathered to protest the event.
Adjunct sociology professor Renee Overdyke was arrested just before 2 PM after attempting to unplug the television screen and was charged with resisting arrest, distrurbing lawful assembly and second degree obstruction of government administration. These charges were later dropped. The event members ended their demonstration just before 3pm and the protesters dispersed soon after.
After these two events, the AWSS 490Z Research Seminar class in the Department of Women's, Gender and Sexuality Studies taught by Dr. Rajani Bhatia conducted interviews for a oral history essay assignment. The purpose of the research was to create a public record from participants and/or witnesses of the protests.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains materials from a Fall 2023 Research Seminar Class taught for the Department of Women's, Gender and Sexuality Studies at UAlbany taught by Dr. Rajani Bhatia. During the course, students interviewed eight participants and/or observers of the political demonstrations and protests that occured in April of the Spring 2023 semester to create a public record of experiences, resulting in audio and video files of the interviews and automated transcripts. Also included are interview conduction materials, photos and videos taken during and after the protests, and news articles from the time of the protests. The collections also contains materials regarding the response from UAlbany administration including a Free Speech Symposium from the Fall 2023 semester, as well as statements from students, the involved student groups, and the Professor that was arrested during the April 14 event.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
All items in this collection were donated to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives in 2024 by Dr. Rajani Bhatia, who taught the AWSS 490Z Research Seminar class in the Department of Women's, Gender and Sexuality Studies.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into four series, each arranged alphabetically.
Albany, New York; Digital Files; UAlbany Student Affairs; UAlbany Student Groups; Transgender people--New York (State); Abortion--New York (State)--Public opinion; Student movements--New York (State)--Albany; College students--Political activity--New York (State)--Albany.
- Oral History Interviews, 2023 Fall
  - Anjalee Modasra Interview, Interviewed by Eòghan Gagne, Fall 2023
  - Ciarra Medrano Interview, Interviewed by Lauren LaForest, Fall 2023
  - Genevieve Bombard Interview, Interviewed by Kamila Akabirova, Fall 2023
  - Jedidah Pacheco Interview, Interviewed by Toni Tudor, Fall 2023
  - Laila Morrison Interview Audio, Interviewed by Abby Biancaniello, Fall 2023
  - Laila Morrison Interview Video, Interviewed by Abby Biancaniello, Fall 2023
  - Maeco Foster Interview, Interviewed by Ciarra Medrano, Fall 2023
  - Oral History Interview Guide, Fall 2023
  - Professor Renee Overdyke Interview Part 1, Interviewed by Tammy Lai, Fall 2023
  - Professor Renee Overdyke Interview Part 2, Interviewed by Tammy Lai, Fall 2023
  - Script to Secure Verbal Consent from Interviewees, Fall 2023
  - Victoria Ralston Interview, Interviewed by Meaghan Schaumburg, Fall 2023
- Photos and Videos Taken by Protesters, 2023 Spring
  - Dance as Protest Video, Recorded by Jedidah Pacheco, 2023 April 4
  - Dorm Windows on Day After Protest, 2023 April 5
  - Drown Out Transphobia Flyer, 2023 April 3
  - Protestors' Posters, 2023 April 4
- Related News Stories and Other Media, 2023 Spring
  - Albany Student Press Article "On-Campus Anti-Abortion Demonstration Stirs Controversy", 2023 April 24
  - Albany Student Press Article "UAlbany Students Protest During On-Campus Turning Point USA Event", 2023 April 7
  - Breitbart Article "Police Arrest Shrieking Left-Wing Professor Accused of Disrupting Pro-Life Event", 2023 April 21
  - Daily Caller Article "Pro-Abortion Professor Screeches, Resists Arrest After Allegedly Trying To Knock Down Pro-Life Display", 2023 April 21
  - Fox News Article "SUNY Albany protesters destroy Bible at free speech event: 'The tolerant left, ladies and gentlemen'", 2023 April 6
  - Ian Haworth Tweets, 2023 April 5
    - "And by "openly transphobic" they mean someone…" Retweet with Comment, 2023 April 5
      - Attached Video, 2023 April 05
    - "Someone also destroyed a Bible for no reason whatsoever.", 2023 April 5
    - "Last night, I was at the University at Albany to speak with @TPUSA…", 2023 April 5
      - Attached Video, 2023 April 05
    - "More irony: shutting down freech speech by screaming…", 2023 April 5
      - Attached Video, 2023 April 05
    - "Things started to get REAL weird when a conga line formed…", 2023 April 5
      - Attached Video, 2023 April 05
    - ""Trans rights are human rights!" They didn't bother to explain…", 2023 April 5
      - Attached Video, 2023 April 05
    - "The most socialist thing I've ever seen is a bunch of deranged students…", 2023 April 5
      - Attached Video, 2023 April 05
    - "While chanting "Ian sucks" (I mean I've seen better trash talk from kindergartners)…", 2023 April 5
      - Attached Video, 2023 April 05
  - Live Action "Activism Professor arrested for allegedly disrupting pro-life event at University at Albany", 2023 May 3
  - The College Fix "Sociology adjunct screeches while being arrested for unplugging pro-life display", 2023 May 3
- Responses and Aftermath, 2023
  - Email from President Havidán Rodríguez, 2023 April 18
  - Email from V.P. of Student Affairs and Chief Diversity Officer, 2023 April 7
  - Free Speech Symposium "Conversation with UAlbany President Havidán Rodríguez", 2023 September 14
  - Free Speech Symposium "Trans Existence as an Act of Free Speech", 2023 September 14
  - Free Speech Symposium Webpage, 2023 September 14
  - Free Speech Symposium Preview Webpage, 2023-09-14
  - Instagram Post of New York State Young Republicans Press Release, 2023 April 5
  - Instagram Post of QueerJoyUA Official Statement, 2023 September 27
  - Instagram Post of Turning Point USA Official Statement, 2023 April 8
  - Message from Student to President Havidán Rodríguez, 2023
  - Professor Renee Overdyke Draft Statement, 2023 April 19
  - Young Democratic Socialists of America Official Response, 2023 April 5